A Guide to the Archibald R. Papers, 1795-1941(bulk 1831-1941)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Archibald R. Rowzie Papers, 1795-1941 (bulk 1831-1941)
The Library of Virginia
52812
5.45 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Biographical Information
Archibald Ritchie Rowzie was born ca. 1830 in Essex County, Virginia to Richard Rouzie (1789-1870) and Janet Ritchie Rouzie. He married Catharine "Kitty" W. Lewis in 1854. Rowzie trained as a medical doctor and served as an Assistant Surgeon during the Civil War. He also served as Postmaster for Mount Landing, Virginia before and after the Civil War, as well as teaching and farming. Rowzie died 15 September 1902.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1795-1941 (bulk 1831-1941), of Archibald R. Rowzie (ca. 1830-1902) of Essex County, Virginia, consisting of accounts, bills, correspondence, genealogical information, medical publications, photographs, and receipts. Also includes material collected by various Rowzie family members including Roll and Minute Books for the Patriotic Order Sons of America, Washington Camp No. 32 1914-1921.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- "A Diagnosis of Diogenes", undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Account Book, 1795, 1856-1868. (Box 9, Folder vol. 1)
- Account Book, 1795-1897. (Box 9, Folder vol. 2)
- Account Book, 1852-1866. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Account Book, 1852-1879. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Account Book, 1860-1863. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Account Book, 1861-1869. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Account Book, 1867-1868. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Account Book, 1868-1870, undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Account Book, 1869-1872. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Account Book, 1872-1875. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Account Book, 1873-1875. (Box 10, Folder vol. 4)
- Account Book, 1878-1890. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Account Book, 1881-1883. (Box 10, Folder vol. 1)
- Account Book, 1882-1885. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Account Book, 1885-1893. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Account Book, 1894. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Account Book, 1896-1897. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Account Book, 1898-1902. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Account Book, 1903. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Account Book, 1903. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Account Book, 1903-1904. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Account Book, 1904. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Account of Mails Received at the Post Office at Mount Landing, Essex County, Virginia, undated. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 1)
- Advertisement--Antikamnia, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Advertisement--George F. Adams & Co., undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Advertisement--Little Gem Self-Inker, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Advertisement--Mellier Drug Company, undated. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Advertisement--Milkmaid Brand Condensed Milk, undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- American Sunday-School Union--"Little Jane Rebuked", 1845. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Announcement of a Special Systematic Course in Ophthalmology, 1889. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Arlington Lodge, No. 102, ca. 1880. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Article of Agreement Board of District School Trustees, 1874-1876. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Assistant Surgeon--Confederate States of America, 1864-1865, undated. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Atlantic Coast Line North and South Train Schedule, 1888. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 2)
- Attendance Book Public School no. 7 Essex County, Virginia, 1878. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Bills and Accounts, 1848-1849. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Bills and Accounts, 1852-1856. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Bills and Accounts, 1857-1859. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Bills and Accounts, 1860-1869. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Bills and Accounts, 1870-1879. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Bills and Accounts, 1880-1889. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Bills and Accounts, 1890-1896. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Bills and Accounts, 1900-1906, undated. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Bonds and Notes, 1855-1901. (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Cards, undated. (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Commission Fourth Division Virginia Militia, 1860-1861. (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Confederate Grave Marker Application for George P. Vaden, 1931. (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Confederate States of America Forms [blank], ca. 1861-1865. (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Contracts, 1859-1901. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1843-1851. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1853-1859. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1860-1865. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1866-1869. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1870-1879. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1880-1885. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1886-1889. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1890-1892. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1893. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1894-1899. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1900-1906. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Court Papers--Essex County, 1871-1892, undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Decorative Art Exhibition Invitation, 1891. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Deed and Plats, 1860-1871. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 3)
- Deeds, 1835-1861. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Deeds and Plats, 1831-1860. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Deering Harvester & Co. Vest Pocket Memoranda [blank], 1899. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Department of Agriculture Report of the Statistician, 1890. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Drawing--"Your Valentine", undated. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Election Count, undated. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Election Tickets--Essex County, Virginia, 1887-1891. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Envelopes--Empty, 1861-1908, undated. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- "Family Guide" Reader, undated. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Farm Account Book, 1862-1890. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Farm Account Book and Almanac, 1907. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Farmers' Alliance Meeting Broadside, 1890. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Farmers' Alliance of Virginia, 1890. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Farmers Club of Central District, Essex County Virginia, 1888. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- "Genius Rewarded or the Story of the Sewing Machine," 1880. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- The Hankins and Harding Families of Lunenburg County, Compiled by B. Wilson, undated. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- The Harding Family of Lunenburg County, Virginia, Compiled by Bennett T. Wilson, undated. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- "Home and Farm" Subscription Form, undated. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- W. H. Hopkins, Son & Co., undated. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Illustrations, undated. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Key to Painting--"The First Prayer in Congress," undated. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 4)
- Leisure Hour Library Catalog, 1888. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Lewis Family Genealogy, undated. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Maria Isabella Lewis Desceased Pensioner Certificate, 1884. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- List of All Voters of Essex County who have been convicted of felony or Petit Larcey, 1884. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- List of Candidates for Graduation, undated. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 5)
- List of Medical Books Belonging to A. R. Rowzie, 1863. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- List of Waiters at A.R. Rowzie and Catherine W. Lewis Wedding, 1854. (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1874. (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1878-1880, undated. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1880. (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1884-1891, undated. (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1887-1889. (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1888-1892. (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1888. (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1890. (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1890-1891. (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1891. (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1891-1892, undated. (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1892-1894. (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1892-1902. (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1895-1900, undated. (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1897-1902, undated. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1898, undated. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1900-1901. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Memorandum and Account Book, 1905, undated. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Memorandum and Account Book, undated. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Memorandum and Account Books [blank], undated. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- The McClellan & Hitt Combination Female Syringe, undated. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- "The McDonough Combined Tellurian, Lunarian, and Cometarium," undated. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Medical College of Virginia Catalog, 1863. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Medical College of Virginia Catalog, 1868. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Medical College of Virginia Lecture Cards, 1862-1865, undated. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Medical License Application and Tax, 1866-1896. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Medical License Application and Tax, 1884-1885. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 6)
- Medical Notebook, 1862-1881. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Medical Pamphlet--"A New and Important Remedy, Lactopeptine," 1875. (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Medical Pamphlet--"A New Remedy for Rheumatism and Rheumatic Affections," undated. (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Medical Pamphlet--"A Selection of Practical Prescriptions," undated. (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Medical Pamphlet--"An Important Discovery in the Pharmacy of Cascara Sagrada," 1901. (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Cincho-Quinine," undated. (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Crystallized Liniment," undated. (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Discriminating Diagnosis," undated. (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Dr. Girdner's Telephonic Bullet Probe," undated. (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Dr. McIntosh's Natural Uterine Supporter," undated. (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Medical Pamphlet--"The Fourth Materia Medica," undated. (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Hand-Book of Eclampsia," 1893. (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Hayden's Viburnum Compound," 1899. (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Hydroleine," undated. (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Hypophosphites," undated. (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Katharmon," undated. (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Medical Pamphlet--"La Grippe Origin, History, Treatment," 1891. (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Medical Clippings for Physicians Reference," 1882. (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Medical Properties and Uses of the Compound Elixir of Phosphates and Calisaya," undated. (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Phospho-Caffein Compound," undated. (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Selected List of Soluble Pills and Granules," undated. (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Soluble Compressed Hypodermic Tablets," undated. (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Soluble Pills and Granules," 1887. (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Medical Pamphlet--"Vitalized Hypophosphites," undated. (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Medical School Notebook, 1863-1864. (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Military Prison Hospital--Camp Lawton Georgia, List of Sick and Wounded for Exchange, 1864. (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1867-1905, undated. (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Missionary Weekly, undated. (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Newspaper Clipping, undated. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Notebook, 1853-1854. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Notebook, 1856-1857. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Notebook, 1856-1882. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Notebook, 1868. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Notebook, 1901. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Pancreobismuth (Frye) Sample, undated. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Patriotic Order Sons of America, Washington Camp, No. 32, 1916-1921, undated. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Patriotic Order Sons of America, Washington Camp, No. 32 Roll and Minute Book, 1912-1917. (Box 11, Folder vol. 1)
- Patriotic Order Sons of America, Washington Camp, No. 32 Roll and Minute Book, 1917-1921. (Box 11, Folder vol. 2)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Photograph--Unidentified, undated. (Box 12)
- Plates of the Arteries, With References; For the Use of Medical Students, 1839. (Box 10, Folder vol. 2)
- Plates of the Cerebro-Spinal Nerves, With References; For the Use of Medical Students, 1837. (Box 10, Folder vol. 3)
- Poems, undated. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Poems sent to Northern Neck News, undated. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Porter Family, Including William Cabell Harding and Mary Cofer Porter Line, undated. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Postmaster Commission, 1861. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 7)
- Post Office Department, Confederate States of America, 1861. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Prescriptions, undated. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Prisoner of War Parole, 1865. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- The Randolphs, abstracted by H.J. Eckenrode, undated. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Receipts, 1838-1839. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Receipts, 1852-1859. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Receipts, 1860-1869. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Receipts, 1870-1876. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Receipts, 1877-1879. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Receipts, 1880-1889, undated. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Receipts, 1890-1899. (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Receipts, 1902-1907. (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Receipts, undated. (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Records & Goldsborough Distillers Catalog, 1889-1890. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Regulations for the Medical Department of the Confederate States Army, 1863. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Resinol Chemical Company Free Sample Card, ca. 1890. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Review of Reviews Subscription Card, undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Rexburg Farm Alliance, 1889-1891, undated. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Rexburg Farm Alliance Roll Book, undated. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Robert Ritchie's Land, undated. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- R. R. Rouzie & Co. Commission Merchants Tags, undated. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Archie Rowzie's Footprint and Lock of Hair,. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- School Papers--Essex County, Virginia, 8. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- "Sharp & Dahme's Catalogue of Medicinal Preparations and Physicians Dose List," 1887. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Sheet Music, undated. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Speech of Hon. J.C.S. Blackburn--"Vindication of the Country's Dead Heroes, Hancock and McClellan," 1888. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Dr. R.R. Stevenson and Andersonville Prison Recollections, undated. (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Stockade Sick Camp List, undated. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Subscription News Company Catalog, 1881. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Surgeon's Commission of the Union Mutual Accident Association, 1887. (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Tax Bills--Essex County, 1855-1875. (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Tax Bills--Essex County, 1876-1895, undated. (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Teacher's Certificates, 1874-1875. (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Teacher's Pocket Record, 1875-1877. (Box 8, Folder 21)
- "Therapy" Subscription Card, ca. 1895. (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Union Mutual Accident Association Certificate, 1887. (Box 1 Oversize, Folder 8)
- "Views of New York" Photo Booklet, undated. (Box 8, Folder 23)
- "Virginia-Carolina Chemical Company Alamanac," 1901. (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Virginia Fire and Marine Insurance Company Application, ca. 1880. (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Voter Registration--E.W. Haskins, ca. 1870. (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Wallet, undated. (Box 8, Folder 27)
- "Warrock's Virginia and North Carolina Almanack," 1855. (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Weller-Stephens Saddle Bags Co., 1892. (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Will--Richard Rouzie, undated. (Box 8, Folder 30)
- George Williamson Certificate of Undertaker, 1903. (Box 8, Folder 31)
- World's Dispensary Medical Association Catalog, undated. (Box 8, Folder 32)